A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of Peter A. Fraenkel FA615
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of Peter A. Fraenkel
1957-1966
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fraenkel, Peter Adolf (1923-2007)
Ford Foundation
FA615
7.89 Cubic Feet 6 record storage boxes
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series by file type. Further arrangement is loosely alphabetical.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Subject Files, 1957-1969
Series II. Educational Modernization Grant, Madrid Field Office Files, 1969-1973
Series III. Photographs
Scope and Contents
Contains subject files, correspondence, trip files, reports, documentation of grants including the educational modernization grant, field office materials and a small selection of photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Through his various positions at Indiana University Bloomington and the Ford Foundation, Peter Fraenkel (1923-2007) established a long career focused on higher education and educational reform. Fraenkel joined the Ford Foundation in 1962 as a Program Advisor in the Latin America Program. For several years, he served as the Foundation's Representative to Peru before moving to the Division of Education and Research where he worked as Assistant to the Vice President. Fraenkel spent his last years at the Foundation as a Program Advisor in the Division of Education and Research, Public Education Program. He was based in Madrid, Spain and directed a project focused on modernizing and improving education in Spain.
Fraenkel served in the Indiana University Bloomington's President's Office both before and after his time at the Ford Foundation. After leaving the Foundation in 1974, he returned to the university and continued his work in Spain as a consultant to the Spanish Minister of Education and Science. This work was funded by a Ford Foundation grant. In 1978, Fraenkel was appointed Assistant to the President at IU. His last position at the university was in the Office of International Programs as Director of Overseas Projects Development.
Fraenkel completed his undergraduate education in 1946 at Indiana University Bloomington where he majored in physics and mathematics. Born in Germany in 1923, he and his family moved to Bolivia in order to escape Nazi persecution. Prior to working at Indiana University, he served as an educational advisor for the American Military Government in Germany after World War II in 1947. Fraenkel died in 2007 after a battle with Alzheimer's disease.
- Subject Files, 1957-1969; I; 6.57 Cubic Feet 5 record storage boxes
  - Announcements -- Invitations, Accepted and Declined, 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Planning Meeting for the Inter-American Linguistics Conference (Washington, DC), 1962 November 2 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- OD-LA Program Discussions -- Dean George Harrison, MIT (Cambridge, MA), 1963 January 4 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Program Discussion on OAS, AID, IADB (Washington, DC), 1963 January 8-9 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Program Discussions with Brookings Institution, AID, and Peace Corps (Washington, DC), 1963 February 11 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Symposium on Latin America, Wellesly College (Wellesley, MA), 1963 February 12-13 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Educational Television (ETV) (Bogota, Colombia), 1963 February 23-March 3 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Mexico City, Mexico, 1963 March 3-5 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Seminar on Higher Education, University of Kansas (Kansas City, Kansas), 1963 March 5-7 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Annual Meeting of North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, 1963 March 17-20 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Meeting at Pan-American Union (Washington, DC), 1963 March 28-30 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Pan-American Union Consultation and Information Meeting (Washington, DC), 1963 April 16-18 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Latin American Conference, Western College for Women (Oxford, Ohio), 1963 April 19-20 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Second Inter-Agency Information Meeting on Central American Activities in Higher Education, Pan American Union (Washington, DC), 1963 June 11 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Center for Applied Linguistics (Washington, DC), 1963 June 17 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Purdue University (Lafayette, Indiana), 1963 June 19-20 (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Linguistics Conference (Cartagena, Colombia) -- Various Papers, 1963 August (Box 1)
  - Conference -- Conference on Higher Edcuation in the American Republics (CHEAR) (Lima, Peru) -- Papers and Other Data, Incl. Photograph, 1964 February (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- A, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- Alvarez, Professor Jose Vincente, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- B, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- C, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- D, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- E, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- F, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- Friedensburg, Dr. F. -- Consul, 1957-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- G, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- H, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- Hays, Jr., John T., 1958-1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- Hesburgh, Reverend Theodore M., 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- I, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- J, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- K, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- L, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- M, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- Morales-Carrion, Arturo, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- N, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- O, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- P, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- Q, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- R, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- Ramirez S., Marco Antonio, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- S, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- T, 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- V, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- W, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- X-Y, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -- Personal -- Z, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Fraenkel, Peter -- Biographical Data -- Photographs, Press Releases Re: Move from Indiana University to the Ford Foundation, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Fraenkel, Peter -- Congratulatory Letters on Appointment to Ford Foundation (March 1, 1962) (Box 2)
  - Fraenkel, Peter -- Congratulatory Letters on Marriage (August 1962) (Box 2)
  - Fraenkel, Peter -- Domestic -- Personal, Incl. Appointments, Marriage Notice, Address and Car Information, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- Alumni Groups -- Indiana University Alumni Club of NY, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- Alumni Groups -- Sons of Indiana, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- Correspondence, General, Incl. Photograph of Campus Building in Snow, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- Correspondence, A-H, 1957-1964 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- Correspondence, G-M, 1958-1964 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- Correspondence, N-Z, 1960-1964 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- Correspondence, President Elvis J. Stahr, Jr., 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- Language Program Proposal and Press Release, circa 1962 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University -- President Herman B. Wells, 1957-1964 (Box 2)
  - Kennedy -- Cuttings on the Assassination of President John F. Kennedy, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Argentina, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Bolivia, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Brazil (also see Brazil Conference - August 1962) (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Caribbean (see also Santo Domingo trip, July 1962) (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Caribbean -- University College of the West Indies, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Central America, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Chile, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Ecuador, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- General, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Mexico, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Paraguay, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Puerto Rico, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Uruguay, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Latin America -- Venezuela, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - National Educational Television and Radio Center (NET), 1962 (Box 2)
  - Overseas Development-Latin America List of Grants, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
  - Peace Corps -- Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Peru -- Memoranda between Verne S. Atwater and Peter Fraenkel, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Postcards -- Personal, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Reports -- Regional Seminar on the Development of University Libraries in Latin America by Peter Fraenkel for UNESCO, 1962 May (Box 2)
  - Social Science Research Council -- ITR Grant to Strengthen Latin American Studies (PA62-359), 1962 (Box 2)
  - Speeches -- "Understanding Latin Americans" -- Annual Forum of the Westchester Branch of AAUW (Scarsdale, NY), 1962 April (Box 2)
  - Speeches -- "Educational Problems of the Developing Countries: Latin America" -- National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (Albany, NY), 1962 November 15-16 (Box 2)
  - Speeches -- "What Lies in the Future for Overseas Programs for Students" -- Council on Student Travel Conference, 1962 December 5-7 (Box 2)
  - Speeches -- Speech Folder, Kansas, 1963 March 5-7 (Box 2)
  - Speeches -- Pan-American Union, Washington, DC Trip, 1963 April 16-18 (Box 2)
  - Speeches -- "Some Educational Trends and Problems in Latin America" -- Western College (Oxford, Ohio), 1963 April 19-20 (Box 2)
  - Speeches -- "Some Observations on the Current Latin American Scene" -- Columbia University Club, 1963 June 12 (Box 2)
  - Speeches -- Speech Material, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Student Organizations -- National, International, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Quito, Ecuador Re: CIESPAL Grant, 1962 May (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Ecuador, 1962 May 22-28 (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic Re: National Autonomous University of Santo Domingo, 1962 July (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Washington, DC (various matters), 1962 September (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Mexico, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Miscellaneous Papers and Letters Re: Trip to Peru (September 12 to October 12, 1963) and Letters Sent to Peter Fraenkel While in Peru and Ecuador, 1963 September 12-October 12 (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Papers on Trip to Peru, 1963 December 3-18 (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Peter Fraenkel's Trip to Cornell University, 1964 May (Box 3)
  - Trips -- Lima Memoranda, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Peru - Field Office Administration, Grant Funding, Foundation Work, Country Status, 1968 October-1969 January (Box 4)
  - Peru - Staff Appointments, Foundation Grants, 1967 October-1968 September (Box 4)
  - Peru - Overseas Development Self-Study, 1966 August-October (Box 4)
  - Peru - Education Grants, Foundation Work, Program Budgets, Country Status Reports, 1963 July-1965 (Box 4)
  - Grant Funding, Latin America and the Caribbean Staff, LAC Situation and Status Reports, Conference papers, 1965 June-1966 June (Box 4)
  - Travel and Study Awards, Grant Funding, Budgets, Conferences, 1966 June-1967 September (Box 4)
  - Consultants, Travel and Study Candidates, Travel and Study Consultants Reports, Resource Institutions, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Colombia - University of the Andes files - Grant Funding, University Administration, 1961-1965 (Box 4)
  - "A Preliminary Study of Colombian Universities", Rodolfo Low-Maus, 1963 November 28 (Box 4)
  - Colombia - Bogota Field Office, Consultants, Grant Funding, Foundation Work in Colombia, 1965 July-1966 September (Box 4)
  - Colombia - Universidad de Valle, 1962-1965 (Box 4)
  - Colombia - Education Grants for Universities, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Colombia - Universidad de Antioquia, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Marginal de la Selva - Traamos de Ingenio, 1968 January (Box 5)
  - Summary of Ford Foundation Program Actions in Peru and Bolivia, 1969 January (Box 5)
  - Notes - Higher Education, Ford Foundation Efforts in Peru, Bolivia, and the rest of South America, 1963-1968 (Box 5)
  - James R. Himes - Employment Evaluation, 1965-1968 (Box 5)
  - Background on Latin America - Education, Religion, Agriculture, Economy, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Letters. Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Activities, Staff, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Ford Foundation documents, reports, Memoranda Re: Overseas Development, 1957-1967 (Box 5)
  - Agrarian University - Graduate Fellowships, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Monthly Reports-Financial Reports Fiscal Year 1969 - Lima, Peru, 1968 September-December (Box 5)
  - Universidad Nacional Mayor de San Marcos and Universidad Agraria - Admission Information, Aptitude Exam, Brochures, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
  - Argentina - Report re: Visit to Argentinian Universities, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Speeches by Ford Foundation employees and others, 1960-1966 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Agricultural Reports re: Latin America, 1965-1967 (Box 5)
  - "The Ford Foundation's Activities in Latin America", 1967 September (Box 5)
  - Representatives Meeting - Beirut, 1967 January (Box 5)
  - Peru - University of San Marcos, 1958-1969 (Box 5)
  - Colombia - Universities, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Colombia - Program Analysis - Colombia Grants, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Peru - Jim Himes Reports, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Peru - Agricultural Development - Reports, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Bolivia - Reports re: Bolivia and Universities, Trip Report, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Bolivia - Trip, 1967 (Box 5)
- Educational Modernization Grant, Madrid Field Office Files, 1969-1973; II; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - Program of Support to Educational Modernization and Reform in Span (Grant 70-305) - Convocatoria, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Program of Support to Educational Modernization and Reform in Span (Grant 70-305) - Attachments including List of Fellows Sponsored, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Program of Support to Educational Modernization and Reform in Span (Grant 70-305) - General Correspondence - Re: Fellows, Project Status Reports and Budget Information, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
- Photographs, III; 0.3 Cubic Feet
  - Peter Fraenkel photograph file (Box 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Images may be related to Indiana University.